[SPEAKER_00]: So, a question someone asked.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems that other people genuinely enjoy life through its ups and downs, and I have often kind of had, well, issues with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that, you know, practice feels like you have to be giving up stuff, renouncing, but then you look around and there are people genuinely happy, enjoying life, going in those directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, some of our videos resonate with me, but it's like, overall, it feels like, well, this person is asking a question, they're not quite ready,
[SPEAKER_00]: To give up the obvious joys and pleasures and ups and downs of life that everybody around them is very happy about and enjoys them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they say that they want at least to try to experience life like everybody else without being caught up in irrational thoughts and emotions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it kind of seems that it's important to become normal, so to speak, before you can practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if they were to take it on now, practice of giving up stuff that they still haven't quite experienced, in that sense, it feels like they would just fall apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any advice?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what's the problem with having irrational thoughts?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, why do you have that value?
[SPEAKER_01]: And why does it stop there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you explain that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, irrational thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for example, what could you describe as that?
[SPEAKER_01]: You lost something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody died.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think the problem is that it's painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would know...
[SPEAKER_01]: Painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would know, I don't want my mind to be revolving around this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would like to...
[SPEAKER_01]: I would like to let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, it keeps doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if that's your value,
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you clearly said it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you want to recognize being like those other people, engaging in normal things, makes it impossible that you won't have irrational tendencies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Well, those are all ups and downs of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes it's up, sometimes down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will have to, as a result of cultivating sensuality, experience irrationality of your own mind, experience pain, experience the exact same things that you said you don't want to have, because of which you're interested in the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to the extent that you have sensuality, you won't be able to have freedom from irrationality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Freedom from pressure, freedom from internal obsessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to recognize that and keep that in mind, because, well, then, it becomes up to you to decide how much of... how much freedom do you actually want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that will determine how much you have to give up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say I want freedom, but the pressure towards
[SPEAKER_00]: Experiencing what other people experience, namely sensuality, obviously, enjoying life, getting, kind of, as I said, interacting with life, is just too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on one end, yes, I understand that the root of the problem is the irrational mind, suffering and all of that, and that root is fundamentally fueled
[SPEAKER_00]: By engaging with the world and sensuality, but as of now, at this stage, that recognition of what the practice is, is just too weak against the pressure of being normal, how the person said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can I just go and be normal and experience everything and practice later, or what what do I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I just
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll grind my teeth and maybe go mad and completely break apart, have a breakdown, and then simply dismiss the whole direction of training forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's just too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I do when it's too much?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, when it's not too much, you... when it is too much, you recognize there are things that won't be too much, that you could still do, that would still
[SPEAKER_01]: So, try and keep an eye and not go as far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not fall as far.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your desires are proliferating when you engage with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just blanket accept
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to stay, like, ten years later, having the same level of desire as when you started.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually going to have made it even harder to give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, essentially, yeah, if you're not willing to take on the practice, well, try to actually stay where you are by restraining further proliferation rather than
[SPEAKER_01]: Just going with it fully.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're saying, if you can't go forward in the right sense of practice, at least don't go backwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least don't cover up where forward is, even if you can't do it right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the the precept of, for example, often translated as misconduct in regard to sexual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people usually interpret it as, well, as long as I'm not
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not cheating on my partner.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Pali very clearly says misconduct in regard to sensual pleasure, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that means you want to keep an eye on are those sensual things that you're engaging with, even if they seem relatively harmless, how much of an animalistic obsession is building up behind them?
[SPEAKER_01]: That, like, you would be willing to even forego forward thinking about consequences and the overall, like, patience and future rewards for the sake of this thing that I need to get right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, how far back you choose to fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this specific scenario, this... so when the person kind of knows what the practice entails, but they just don't want to do it, they don't feel ready to do it, they should, well, make themselves ready gradually.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, they know they'll engage with centrality, because they haven't built up the restraint and the value.
[SPEAKER_00]: They know it will offer a relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: They know it will be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: They know that doesn't matter how much they read about the danger, they will... they're not gonna see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're saying, what they should do, in that kind of scenario, where they will inevitably fail, in terms of precepts and celibacy, they should prevent themselves from falling too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, consider the implications, secondary implications, of your impending failure, that you will willingly choose, because the mind is weak, and go back to addiction and so on, and then try to minimize the distance that you would have to come back from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're saying that's what kāma-sūmi-cācāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's... looking at your intentions already, how obsessive, passionate, and... and... understrained they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, could you give some practical example of that, in terms of... yeah, like, say, central desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, either way, it's a, as we said, it's a choosing to, kind of, go back to centrality or choosing to fail, but what would constitute successful kāma-sumi-cācara?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the line?
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean, at which point would they... Yeah, so, out of the five precepts... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When would be against the precept?
[SPEAKER_00]: When it becomes misconduct in centrality, that precept, because it's obviously vague.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well,
[SPEAKER_00]: With some examples?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, a concrete example would be the very common modern addiction towards pornography, masturbation, things that you see that when you give in to them, the result is more pressure to keep engaging with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's gonna happen whenever you touch sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But where is the line when...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, now I gave in within the third precept of a, you know, non-practicing householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, trying to practice householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily non-practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when is the... within the precept?
[SPEAKER_00]: And when is... oh, this is now against the third precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, it's gonna feel, you know, you gave in to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when does it become against the third precept, in the five precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, giving in is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Giving in, to some extent, is within the third householder precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: But crossing that extent, it's against.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you... when do you... how do you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you confess the third, like, breaking of the third precept of layman's precept, kamasumi cācara?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, but that's the thing, like, it's... how would you categorize different levels of obsession objectively?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's about obsession.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where's the line?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, giving in once, you'll be doing it out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Giving it ten times, it's out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I give it ten times?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is five times the line?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or two times?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where's the line?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a line?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How easy would it be for you to stop?
[SPEAKER_01]: That specific thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it become an addiction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you still recognize, okay, I could still, even if I have desire for it, I could still choose not to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously you can't, because then you'll be actually celibate and practicing towards the dhamma rightly with the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but there is a difference between, like, okay, I'll give in to saṃśvādhi either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this specific thing now, I can't live without.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, how is that against the precept?
[SPEAKER_00]: How is that misconduct?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because it takes you towards a level of, not just overall dependence, but being like an animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where an animal, it's almost like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, would just giving in once make an animal?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... Like, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference is, a human can have a desire for something, recognize
[SPEAKER_01]: For whatever reason, I shouldn't engage with it, because it's going to lead to greater harm in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, an animal... No, I know that, but that's... you're still talking on the universal level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is universally true for giving in once or a hundred times.
[SPEAKER_00]: But we're talking about the precepts that technically allows you to give in, to some extent, because you're unable to be celibate and actually practice, like, the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're working towards it, so you're using five precepts to train towards the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they do actually allow you some extent of giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the line?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't apply the universal truth, or you're going to... because it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you give in once or a hundred times, universal principle is yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're giving into sensuality and stuff, and from that universal point of view, it's all wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for somebody who gradually trains towards the eight precepts, some extent is allowable.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that extent?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can a person, for themselves, develop, discern the criteria of where the extent of kāma-sumicācara is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I mean, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I would see it as the extent of the obsession, but how can you quantify that as a... as a measure that somebody would be able to tell, like you said, oh, I confess it because I saw that it crossed that specific line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the extent of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, get back to that and maybe what would be, say, like a daily example of somebody, how they go about
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to keeping the extent of obsession in check...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, just imagine yourself, like, say, you want to... you want to do something during the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a desire, there is a compulsion, there's pressure to give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you are self-aware, you know that you need to work towards the Eight Precepts, you can't just overnight undertake it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know you will give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you keep yourself in check?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already an obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already coming out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you keep yourself in check, whereby that obsession that you know you will give in, does not become the obsession that now violates kāma-sumicācara?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I mean, I guess you could come up with various measures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, can you postpone it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's one practical way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I meant with an animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, an animal
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to give in at that very moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you postpone it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I... can I wait a bit?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you have something else?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I can't postpone it, if it feels like I can't postpone it, would then even giving in once be against kamasumi cācara?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it is the extent of obsession as measured, then yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it would.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no quantity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if there were quantity, basically written within Kāma-sumicācara, it wouldn't serve the practical purpose of training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why even being celibate,
[SPEAKER_00]: It can still be on the level of sīlabhāta paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you're not training in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not taking on those values.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not doing this, and then abstaining from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you give in, or within the precepts of kamasumi cācara, you could recognize, okay, somebody might actually give in multiple... do certain things multiple times.
[SPEAKER_00]: And still not necessarily be against kamasamhicacara.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on different occasions, the same thing, depending on the level of obsession, the animality of the mind, the obsession behind it, it's like even giving once would be misconduct in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's this point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't quantify it by any external measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can quantify it by recognizing the extent of the pressure, the extent of the urgency.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you said, can you postpone it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are there any other practical considerations, questions, reflections they can do, again, to clarify where the line is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you do something else to appease that pressure, rather than that specific thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would an alternative to that which you want satisfy the desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Less harmful, you could say.
[SPEAKER_01]: A less harmful alternative, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there any, even mundane, negative consequence that would come from you doing that action, that you would have to ignore?
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that sounds like the first thing you should probably think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Potentially upsetting other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting blamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess you could say, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: The degree of embarrassment you would feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody saw you doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's an animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, an animal doesn't care who's watching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, when one is gradually... inevitably having to gradually work towards the eight precepts, the... you would be... you would have to be giving up to... giving in, sorry, to the animal's pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, even that does not justify loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or more loss than you already... Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthering of the loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: You could then even ask yourself, say you have a desire to eat something very specific, because also, factually, you are hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the animal mind is factually hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the body is hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal wants to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta is pressuring you towards food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would know for a fact that if you were to eat anything, it would actually satisfy the hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's agreeable stuff, you don't have to eat stuff that you hate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not eat that specific, like, extra specific things that you crave to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on one way, you would provide a satisfaction to the pressure and the animal, even out of a degree of weakness, but on another way, you wouldn't allow it that cherry on top that really want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that principle can actually be applied in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wanna... again, you're not able to keep the eight precepts, it's too much pressure, it's too painful, taking on five, but not blindly, like a just sort of mindless, self-declared religious Buddhist, but actually the one that wants to train.
[SPEAKER_00]: Music, uh... entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, there's specific things you want, out of boredom, out of anxiety, out of all these unwholesome bases that, of course, you have to deal with, if you actually want to practice for Sotāpati, at some point, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you have to give in, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just too much, as we said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even then, you could start applying the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need a distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is just getting too... too unpleasant, too forceful, too strong.
[SPEAKER_00]: To what extent you allow that... that desire to be satisfied?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the average person's point of view, that would already be a training, because... That would be a training, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the... that's the difference between keeping the precepts and training in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intention is taking them as a standard.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inevitably, you will feel, when you give in, you will feel relieved,
[SPEAKER_00]: To some extent, because again, you are a craving, acting out of compulsion that gets appeased.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would feel relieved, you would feel satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you pay attention to the extent of your engagement with the sense objects, try and change, try and kind of relegate the sense object down from the one that you want,
[SPEAKER_00]: And force your mind to not quite get what it wanted through and through, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And build up on that.